In the last couple videos, we
前回までのビデオで
talked about the ideas of
まずは映画のフィーチャーが与えられた時
how, first, if you're
それを用いて
given features for movies, you
ユーザーのパラメータのデータを
can use that to learn parameters data for users.
学習する事が出来る、という話をした。
And second, if you're given parameters for the users,
次に、ユーザーのパラメータを与えられたら、
you can use that to learn features for the movies.
それを使って映画のフィーチャーを学習する事が出来る、という話をした。
In this video we're going
このビデオでは、これら二つのアイデアを
to take those ideas and put
用いて、それらを合わせて
them together to come up
協調フィルタのアルゴリズムに
with a collaborative filtering algorithm.
たどり着く。
So one of the things we worked
つまり以前やった事の
out earlier is that if
一つには
you have features for the
映画のフィーチャーがあれば、
movies then you can solve
最小化問題を解く事で
this minimization problem to find
ユーザーのパラメータである
the parameters theta for your users.
シータを見つける事が出来た。
And then we also
そしてその次に、
worked that out, if you
パラメータであるシータがあれば、
are given the parameters theta,
それを用いて
you can also use that to
フィーチャーxを推計する事が
estimate the features x, and
出来るのだった。
you can do that by solving this minimization problem.
それは最小化問題を解く事で出来るのだった。
So one thing you
だから取りうる手段として一つ考えられるのは
could do is actually go back and forth.
行ったり来たりして実行する事だ。
Maybe randomly initialize the parameters
ランダムに初期化されたパラメータで、
and then solve for theta,
シータについて解き、
solve for x, solve for theta,
xについて解き、シータについて解き、
solve for x. But, it
xについて解く。
turns out that there is a
だが、シータとxを
more efficient algorithm that doesn't
行ったり来たりしなくても良い
need to go back and forth
もっと効率的なアルゴリズムがある事が
between the x's and the
知られている、それは行ったり来たりする代わりに
thetas, but that can solve
シータとxを同時に
for theta and x simultaneously.
解く事が出来る。
And here it is. What we are going to do, is basically take
それはこんなだ。 我らがやる事は、基本的には
both of these optimization objectives, and
これら二つの最適化の目的関数をとり、
put them into the same objective.
それを一つの目的関数に突っ込む、という事だ。
So I'm going to define the
つまり私は、新しい最適化の目的関数Jを
new optimization objective j, which
定義する、
is a cost function, that
それはフィーチャーxと
is a function of my features
パラメータのシータに関する
x and a function
関数としての、
of my parameters theta.
コスト関数だ。
And, it's basically the two optimization objectives
そして基本的には上の所に
I had on top, but I put together.
二つの最適化の目的関数があったが、それを一つにくっつけた。
So, in order to
これを説明する為に、
explain this, first, I want to point out that this
まず以下の二つの項が同じという事を指摘したい：
term over here, this squared
この項、この二乗誤差の項と、
error term, is the same
この二乗誤差の項、
as this squared error term and the
これ。
summations look a little bit
和の取り方がちょっと違って見えるが、
different, but let's see what the summations are really doing.
この和が実際に何をやっているかを見てみよう。
The first summation is sum
最初の和は、
over all users J and
全てのユーザーjに渡ってとっている、
then sum over all movies rated by that user.
そして次にそのユーザーによってレーティングされた全ての映画について和を取る。
So, this is really summing over all
つまり、これは実際は、ユーザーにレーティングされた
pairs IJ, that correspond
全ての映画に対応した
to a movie that was rated by a user.
iとjのペアに渡って和を取っている。
Sum over J says, for every
jに渡って取る和は、各ユーザに対して、と言っていて
user, the sum of
そしてそのユーザーがレーティングした
all the movies rated by that user.
全ての映画に渡って和を取る。
This summation down here, just does things in the opposite order.
この下の和は、それを反対の順番でやるだけだ。
This says for every movie
これが言っているのは、各映画iに対して
I, sum over all
その映画をレーティングした全てのユーザーj
the users J that have
に渡って
rated that movie and so, you
和をとる、つまり、
know these summations, both of these
これらの和は、これらは両方とも、
are just summations over all pairs
r i jがイコール1な
ij for which
全てのi jのペアに渡って
r of i J is equal to 1.
和を取るだけ。
It's just something over all the
それはようするに、
user movie pairs for which you have a rating.
レーティングを持っている全てのユーザーと映画の組に渡って和を取る。
and so those two terms
つまりこれら二つの項は
up there is just
この最初の項と
exactly this first term, and
完全に一致している。
I've just written the summation here explicitly,
そして私は和を明示的に書いた、
where I'm just saying the sum
それはようするに、r i j がイコール1となる
of all pairs IJ, such that
全てのi jのペアに渡って
RIJ is equal to 1.
和を取る、と言っている。
So what we're going
我らがやりたい事は
to do is define a
xとシータを同時に解く為に
combined optimization objective that
最小化をする対象となる、
we want to minimize in order
最適化の複合目的関数を
to solve simultaneously for x and theta.
定義するという事だ。
And then the other terms in
そして最適化の目的関数に残ってる
the optimization objective are this,
他の項はこれだ。
which is a regularization in terms of theta.
これはシータの正規化項だ。
So that came down here and
それはここに来る。
the final piece is this
そして最後のピースとなるのは
term which is
この項で、これは
my optimization objective for
xの為の最適化の目的関数の中に残ってる物で
the x's and that became this.
それはここに来る。
And this optimization objective
そしてこの最適化の目的関数Jは
j actually has an interesting property
興味深い性質を持っている、それは
that if you were to hold
xを定数に
the x's constant and just
固定してみて、
minimize with respect to the thetas then
シータに関して最小化してみると、
you'd be solving exactly this problem,
するとまさにこの問題を解いている事になる。
whereas if you were to do
一方、その反対をやると、
the opposite, if you were to
シータを仮に定数で
hold the thetas constant, and minimize
固定してみて、Jを
j only with respect to
xに関してだけ
the x's, then it becomes equivalent to this.
最小化してみると、
Because either this term
この項か、またはこの項が
or this term is constant if
xに関してかシータに関してのどちらかに関してだけ最小化するなら、
you're minimizing only the respective x's or only respective thetas.
定数になるから。
So here's an optimization
だから、これが、xに関するコスト関数と
objective that puts together my
シータに関するコスト関数を
cost functions in terms of x and in terms of theta.
くっつけた最適化の目的関数だ。
And in order to
そして一つの最適化問題に
come up with just one
帰着される為には、
optimization problem, what we're going
我らがやるべき事は、
to do, is treat this
このコスト関数を
cost function, as a
フィーチャーxとユーザーのパラメータシータの
function of my features
両方に関する
x and of my user
関数として
pro user parameters data and
扱う事だ。
just minimize this whole thing, as
そして単純に全体を
a function of both the
xとシータの関数として、
Xs and a function of the thetas.
最小化すれば良い。
And really the only difference
そして実際、これと
between this and the older
以前のアルゴリズムの
algorithm is that, instead
唯一の違いは、
of going back and forth, previously
行ったり来たりする代わりに、
we talked about minimizing with respect
以前のはシータに関して最小化した後
to theta then minimizing with respect to x,
次にxについて最小化して、
whereas minimizing with respect to theta,
その後シータについて最小化して、
minimizing with respect to x and so on.
xについて最小化して、、、などとやったのだったが、
In this new version instead of
この新しいバージョンでは、
sequentially going between the
xとシータという二つのパラメータのセットの間を
2 sets of parameters x and theta,
順番に行ったり来たりする代わりに
what we are going to do
たんに両方の
is just minimize with respect
パラメータに関して
to both sets of parameters simultaneously.
同時に最小化する、という事をする。
Finally one last detail
最後に一つ詳細な話だが、
is that when we're learning the features this way.
フィーチャーをこういう風に学ぶ場合、
Previously we have been using
以前はx0がイコール1となる
this convention that
コンベンションを使っていて、
we have a feature x0 equals
これは切片項に
one that corresponds to an interceptor.
対応した物だった。
When we are using this
この種の定式化を用いる時には、
sort of formalism where we're are actually learning the features,
実際にはフィーチャーも学習する事になるので、
we are actually going to do away with this convention.
このコンベンション無しでいける。
And so the features we are going to learn x, will be in Rn.
だから我らの学習する事になるフィーチャーxはR nだ。
Whereas previously we had
一方、以前はフィーチャーxは
features x and Rn + 1 including the intercept term.
R n+1だった、切片項を含んでいたから。
By getting rid of x0 we now just have x in Rn.
そこからx0を取り除いたから、xはR nとなる。
And so similarly, because the
そして同様に、
parameters theta is in
パラメータのシータは
the same dimension, we now
同じ次元なので、
also have theta in RN
シータも R nとなる。
because if there's no
何故ならx0が無いなら、
x0, then there's no need
シータ0も同様に
parameter theta 0 as well.
不要だからだ。
And the reason we do away
そしてこのコンベンション無しで
with this convention is because
いける理由としては、
we're now learning all the features, right?
いまや我らはフィーチャーを全て学習する事になった、よね？
So there is no need
だからいつも1と等しくなるフィーチャーを
to hard code the feature that is always equal to one.
ハードコードする必要が無い。
Because if the algorithm really wants
何故ならもしアルゴリズムが
a feature that is always equal
いつも1となるフィーチャーを本当に必要としているなら、
to 1, it can choose to learn one for itself.
それは自身で勝手にそう学習するはずだからだ。
So if the algorithm chooses,
だからもしアルゴリズムがそう選べば
it can set the feature X1 equals 1.
x1=1とセットされる。
So there's no need
だからフィーチャーx0を1と
to hard code the feature of
ハードコードする必要は無い。
001, the algorithm now has
アルゴリズムはそれを自分自身で学習する事が出来るだけの
the flexibility to just learn it by itself. So, putting
柔軟性がある。
everything together, here is
では全部を合わせると、
our collaborative filtering algorithm.
これが協調フィルタリングのアルゴリズムだ。
first we are going to
まず、xとシータを
initialize x and
ある小さなランダムの値で
theta to small random values.
初期化する。
And this is a little bit
これはちょっと
like neural network training, where there
ニューラルネットワークのトレーニングに似てるね。
we were also initializing all the parameters of a neural network to small random values.
そこでもニューラルネットワークのパラメータを全て小さなランダムの数で初期化したんだった。
Next we're then going
次に、コスト関数を、
to minimize the cost function using
最急降下法なりアドバンスドな最適化のアルゴリズムなりを使って
great intercepts or one of the advance optimization algorithms.
最小化する。
So, if you take derivatives you
だから微分をとれば、
find that the great intercept
こんな感じの
like these and so this
最急降下法の更新ルールが得られる。
term here is the
この項は、コスト関数を
partial derivative of the cost function,
偏微分した物。
I'm not going to write that out,
全部書いたりはしないが、
with respect to the feature
それをフィーチャーx(i) kで
value Xik and similarly
偏微分した物だ。
this term here is also
同様に、この項もまた、
a partial derivative value of
コスト関数を偏微分した物で
the cost function with respect to the parameter
今度はパラメータであるシータに関して
theta that we're minimizing.
偏微分した物で、それに関して最小化する。
And just as a reminder, in
ちょっと注意を。
this formula that we no
この式では、もはや
longer have this X0 equals
x0イコール1が無い、
1 and so we have
だからxはR nとなり、
that x is in Rn and theta is a Rn.
シータもR nとなる。
In this new formalism, we're regularizing
この新しい定式化では、各パラメータ、シータも、
every one of our perimeters theta, you know, every one of our parameters Xn.
各パラメータx nも、正規化している。
There's no longer the special
もはやシータ0の特別扱いのケースも
case theta zero, which was
存在しない。シータ0は異なる風に
regularized differently, or which
正規化していたんだった。
was not regularized compared to
それはシータ1からシータnのようには
the parameters theta 1 down to theta.
正規化しないんだった。
So there is now no longer a
もはやシータ0は存在しないので、
theta 0, which is why
そんな訳だからこのアップデートでも
in these updates, I did not
k=0の特別なケースの
break out a special case for k equals 0.
場合分けをしていない。
So we then use gradient descent
そして最急降下法を使って
to minimize the cost function
コスト関数Jを
j with respect to the
フィーチャーxとパラメータシータに関して
features x and with respect to the parameters theta.
最小化していく。
And finally, given a
そして最後に、あるユーザーに対して
user, if a user
ユーザーがあるパラメータ、シータを
has some parameters, theta, and
持っているなら、
if there's a movie with
そして映画にはある種の
some sort of learned features x,
学習されたフィーチャーxがあるなら、
we would then predict that that
そのユーザーが映画に
movie would be given a
星いくつのレーティングをするかを
star rating by that user
シータjの転置と、、、
of theta transpose j. Or
または、前の表記と
just to fill those in,
合わせると、
then we're saying that if user
もしユーザーjがまだ
J has not yet
映画iをレーティング
rated movie I, then
していなければ、
what we do is predict that
ユーザーjは映画iを
user J is going to
シータjの転置 xi と
rate movie I according to
レーティングすると
theta J transpose Xi.
予測する。
So that's the collaborative
以上が協調フィルタリングアルゴリズムだ。
filtering algorithm and if
もしこのアルゴリズムを
you implement this algorithm you actually get a pretty
実装すれば、おそらく全ての映画の
decent algorithm that will simultaneously
良いフィーチャーと
learn good features for hopefully
全てのユーザーのパラメータを同時に
all the movies as well as
学習する、かなり良いアルゴリズムを
learn parameters for all the
得る事が出来る。
users and hopefully give
そして別々のユーザーが別々の映画を
pretty good predictions for how
どうレーティングするかの
different users will rate different movies that they have not yet rated
かなり良い予測を与える事も期待出来る。